<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Scrolling Text</string>
    <string name="article_title"><b>Fukushima disaster: What happened at the nuclear plant?</b></string>
    <string name="article_subtitle"><b>Ten years ago, on a Friday afternoon in March, the most powerful earthquake ever recorded in Japan struck off the countrys eastern coast.</b></string>
    <string name="article_text">The 9.0-magnitude quake was so forceful it shifted the Earth off its axis. It triggered a tsunami which swept over the main island of Honshu, killing more than 18,000 people and wiping entire towns off the map.

At the Fukushima nuclear power plant, the gigantic wave surged over defences and flooded the reactors, sparking a major disaster. Authorities set up an exclusion zone which grew larger and larger as radiation leaked from the plant, forcing more than 150,000 people to evacuate from the area.

A decade later, that zone remains in place and many residents have not returned. Authorities believe it will take up to 40 years to finish the work, which has already cost Japan trillions of yen.
    There were no deaths immediately during the nuclear disaster. At least 16 workers were injured in the explosions, while dozens more were exposed to radiation as they worked to cool the reactors and stabilise the plant.

Three people were reportedly taken to hospital after high-level exposure.

Long-term effects of the radiation are a matter of debate. The World Health Organization (WHO) released a report in 2013 that said the disaster will not cause any observable increase in cancer rates in the region. Scientists both inside and outside Japan believe that aside from the region immediately around the plant, the risks of radiation remain relatively low.

On 9 March 2021, ahead of the 10-year anniversary, a UN report said there had been no adverse health effects documented among Fukushima residents directly related to the radiation from the disaster. Any future radiation-related health effects were unlikely to be discernible, it said.

Fukushima exclusion worse than radiation?
Fukushimas long road to recovery
Growing crops in the shadow of Fukushima
But many believe the dangers are far greater, and residents remain wary. Though officials have lifted restrictions in many areas most people have not returned to their homes. In 2018, the Japanese government announced that one worker had died after exposure to radiation and agreed his family should be compensated.

A number of people are however confirmed to have died in the evacuation, including dozens of hospital patients who had to be moved due to fears of radiation.</string>

</resources>